Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today we're
going to be learning about the concept
behind colligative properties, which
relates molality, a concentration
term for solutions, and how these
different solutes are going to be
dissolved and dissociate in solution.
Now, when they dissolve, what
happens is they break down into
individual ions or particles.
which can disrupt the intermolecular
force networks within a solvent.
Now, when that happens, there's
all sorts of different unique
properties that you probably take
advantage of in your everyday life
that get manipulated as a result.
So just to kind of give you some
ideas of these, so a lot of them
are actually things you probably
do around you right now, possibly.
So, let's say when it's really
cold in the winter time and
you need to salt the roads.
Well, the reason that they add salt
to water, which is the solvent,
it's going to disrupt the hydrogen
bonding that occurs between water.
Therefore, it makes it really hard
for water to freeze because all
those little salt particles are
causing ion dipole force to have.
It lowers the freezing point.
It changes it.
If you add antifreeze to a car, the
more of adding the solute, it does
something a little bit similar.
It makes it so it's harder for the car to
either overheat, or even freeze on you.
So that way your engine doesn't
have any kind of weird effect.
It changes that boiling point
elevate, it elevates the boiling
point and lowers the freezing point.
Another concept is if you'd love
to eat different pickled foods.
So like, maybe if you like pickling
jalapenos or just making pickles or any
of these types of different crunchy foods.
Well, essentially these different
substances absorb the water out
of all these different molecules
and in the process cause them to
get a different texture change,
it changes their flavor, it has a
major effect on how we can see them.
And that's what we're going to be
talking about in this video is how all
these different properties are affected
by the solute solvent interaction.
So let's take a look at it and stay
tuned and please feel free to learn
all about colligative properties.
Let's take a look.
The
first concept we're going to talk
about is boiling point elevation.
So now what this is all about is when
you dissolve a solute in a solution.
It's going to actually increase
the boiling point of the solution.
So the L it's going to get
elevated and go up to the sky.
Now why does this entire thing happen?
So what we want to think about is
molecules when they are in solution,
can it change the boiling point?
What exactly, why would that happen?
Well, what this implies is that
it's actually, it's going to, that
means it's more difficult for a
molecule to go into the gas phase.
Okay.
Thanks.
Right?
When something boils, it's
going from a liquid to a gas.
So now, why would this all happen?
Well, we got to try to remember that
intermolecular forces are at play when we
are talking about these solutions, right?
Waters are hydrogen bonding to each other.
There's an interaction here,
meaning like dissolves like.
So if I add a solute to the mix.
Well, what's changing here?
Well, instead of hydrogen bonding that
is possible, now we're going to have
ion dipole forces, which are possible,
which if you remember, ion dipole
forces are stronger than hydrogen
bonding, meaning that they're going
to have a preference and it's going
to change how these are interacting.
Let's take a look exactly
what I'm talking about here.
So the way that we look at this,
so if I have a solution that every,
all these individual water molecules
are all hydrogen bonding together,
they're interacting, they are holding
each other in side the liquid phase,
meaning that it's actually very
difficult for them to become a guest.
It takes a lot of energy
for that to happen, right?
In order for something to gain enough
energy to go in, to be vaporized.
it takes a lot of energy to do so.
So when you have, let's say
something like water, it usually
takes a, it's about a hundred
degrees Celsius for it to be boiled.
Now, if I decide to add salt to water,
which you do all the time when you make
pasta or rice, well, most of us do it
because of the flavor profile, right?
We like it when the water actually
has a little bit of flavor to it.
Now, the other reason you do it is
because it actually can raise the
boiling point slightly of water.
Meaning that it will cook your pasta or
rice at a slightly higher temperature,
therefore maintaining also the
water level inside the pot as well.
Now what is exactly happening there is
essentially if I take these little yellow
dots here, which you can kind of see
all around here, these are your solutes
that are in the side of the solution.
So solute, as in these
are your, your salt ions.
And so like you can pretend they're
like, and a plus or chlorine or
whatever ion you want to pick.
Choose your favorite.
Now when you place those into solution,
now you have ion dipole forces.
These are much stronger as a result.
They're tougher.
There's something that's a much
higher force than hydrogen bonding.
Meaning, it's harder for
them to let go of water.
They don't want to let go at all.
Um, when essentially you have a liquid,
one way to kind of think about it
is when they're trying to be a gas.
It's like essentially if you were to try
to pick up a kid at a, at a sleepover and
they've been staying there all night and
they're like, please don't take me home.
Don't take me home.
Well, it's a very similar concept here.
The salt is going to be holding
on to the water molecules like,
no, it doesn't want them to leave.
It's a similar idea.
So the stronger the intermolecular
force, the harder it is.
So the question I would ask is how
does the present of a solute affect the
kinetic energy of water trying to boil?
And essentially it requires
more of it to happen.
It holds things back because
the forces are stronger, going
to take more temperature to be
able to leave the gas phase.
And that's one way we
want to think about it.
And as we move forward, so with
this concept, just to wrap it up.
So one way that we can look at it
is solutions will have a higher
boiling point than pure water.
So pure water, it's general boiling
points around a hundred degrees Celsius.
So I drew a little line here.
To help illustrate that, Hey,
this is at a hundred degrees.
So the second that we end up adding
some salt or a solute to water, what's
going to happen is you're going to see
an overall increase of that temperature.
It's going to go up as a result.
So let's kind of maybe draw that
as white here instead of purple.
So it goes up.
Now, if I add more salt and it dissolves,
so the more and more you add, that
temperature is going to go higher.
So one thing that we see here is the
higher the concentration, the the more
it's the temperature is going to raise.
So higher, higher a concentration
is a higher temperature.
Okay.
Now, when it comes to a higher
concentration, we measure this
for colligative properties in
molality when that happens.
Okay.
So that's a, uh, cursive, uh, M
when we talk about molality and
the higher that is, is the higher
temperature that is behind it.
So the more concentration,
more temperature because it's
holding those molecules back.
So let's take a look at all the
concepts we need here to be able
to determine colligative properties
and how it affects things.
So the first concept was that higher
molality means aka more solute has a
big effect on colligative properties.
Now, this isn't the only thing
we're looking at as well, we have
to remember that solubility is
important as well, meaning how do
these different molecules interact.
How do they end up actually
like breaking apart in solution?
So one thing to think of is more
soluble the particles are, or the
ions, the greater the boiling point.
So what we have to do is, is understand
how we can write solubility equations.
So I have a couple here.
And what you are going to be doing
is you need to count how many, how
many different particles or ions
are formed when it is soluble.
So is understanding electrolytes
as well, which if you need a review
on that, go to my other, go back
to my other video on electrolytes
to be able to understand that.
So when, what we're looking at
when you write out your solubility
equation is you're counting
how many particles are formed.
So let's say if I look at this
first one, we have glucose, which
is a non electrolyte, meaning
that it does not become ionized.
But it's polar, so it's dissolved.
So when that dissolves, notice how
we just have now aqueous glucose.
So what we are going to do is count
how many particles were formed.
And what we see is, well,
there is one particle formed.
So what this means is that
it has an I equal to one.
Now to go to the next one
for counting again, if I take
sodium chloride, it's soluble.
So it's going to break down
into, into, uh, sodium.
And chlorine as my two ions.
And how many do you have?
Well, we have one, two ions,
so that means you're going to
have an i value equal to two.
We're just counting.
Now if I do the next one, calcium
acetate, well, this one we have one
calcium forming and two acetate ions,
meaning you have a total of eight.
three particles that are formed.
On the last one, we have iron chloride.
So it's one iron, three
chlorines that are here.
This one is going to
be I is equal to four.
Sorry, the last one was
I is equal to three.
This one's I is equal to four.
All right.
So we're adding the coefficients together.
Now, why is this important?
Well, the effect here is the more
particles you have in solution is the
more disruption that's going to be
caused within the intermolecular forces.
So one thing that you're going to see
is the higher the I value, the more, the
higher the boiling point is going to be.
So essentially as we're kind
of moving this way, right?
So down towards, uh, more I values,
we're going to have a higher, Boiling
point on the bottom of the more ions,
the higher the boiling point, and this
is going to take a higher priority
over the concentration as well.
If your concentrations are very close,
let's say if we had all four of these
solutions, Well, and like, maybe if
it's like all like two, for example.
The I is equal to four will have a greater
impact because they're all about the same.
So usually we always go by how
many particles are being formed.
So what is your ionization factor?
Can you count right?
How many ions are there?
Um, and then if you need help with
solubility and understanding how
to use solubility rules, refer to
my other videos in this playlist to
be able to master those skills too.
All right, let's take a
look at the next concept.
Freezing point depression is the next one.
So if the boiling point goes up.
The freezing melting point can go down.
So it's the same idea here.
If we dissolve a substance in water, so we
will lower the freezing point, especially
when you compare it to pure water.
And when I say pure, that means that
it's the only substance in that water.
Now, why does that happen?
Well, when solute to the mix.
It's going to prevent hydrogen bonding,
where you see we have a little solid
hydrogen over here as an ice cube, right?
When you add ions, it stops it.
This is why they salt roads during the
winter and colder climates because,
you know, ice is a big hazard for
when you're driving cause you just
slip it cause crashes, but if you salt
the roads, it will help prevent it
from freezing or take a lot longer.
So usually you'll see a big layer of
salt all over the roads and during
wintertime, like in the Northeast
of the U S or in Europe, or even in
Northern or the Northern Midwest,
um, even in the mountains around
California, you will see, you will
see them salting, salting the roads.
So when this happens, well, it's
going to be the same idea, but
opposite of what you saw earlier.
So pure water freezes at about a hundred.
And then if you add a little bit
of solute, well, it would go down.
Let's say a little tiny bit
to maybe, uh, just a little
lower than the freezing point.
You'll see it maybe
about by a degree or two.
Typically, it depends on the solute.
So this is solute specific.
Um, in our course, I'm not worried about
you guys calculating it, but if you
have to take general chemistry, that is
something that you will have to calculate.
That's a pretty easy formula to use.
It just goes off the number of particles.
Times that by molality
and then times a constant.
The last concept is on osmosis.
So when you are trying to learn about
osmosis, this is a very important
concept for anyone interested in
the health sciences and biology
because this is a huge concept that's
used for how your body functions,
especially for how your cells work.
So all this is, is about how
a semi permeable membrane.
which means when we say permeable means
that something can pass through it.
Now it's to some things, that's
why it's the semi part of it.
So it allows certain molecules to pass
all your vital organs and your cells.
Generally, usually act like a membrane.
So now one, how is a semi permeable?
Well, what happens is Is that water
can move through it, but nothing else.
So I have two sides of a chamber
here, and then this black line in
the middle is my membrane right here.
Now what's happening is that water
can essentially can move from the
left, it can move to the right, it
can free flow between the two sides.
It's like in a dynamic
equilibrium when that happens.
So when we say that water is free, it's
because it can move where it wants.
However, we're talking about
colligative properties.
So what happens if I add a solute?
When we add a solute, water favors
dissolving it, meaning that if I have
NACL, it will want to dissolve it.
It will rush to it.
It will clump around it.
So what will happen is if I
have, let's say an area of high
salt concentration on the left.
So you see the purple.
And the green dots here.
So there's more salt.
So what's going to happen
here as a result, the water
is going to rush through it.
And if you remember this semi permeable
membrane, it allows water to pass.
So all of the water is going
to go from an area of low salt
to high salt concentration.
So it's all going to go.
in towards towards the
left hand side as a result.
So let's see what this
is going to look like.
So what you're going to see is
after that raises all the water
all of a sudden is all on the left.
Notice how much higher it is.
So if you can imagine this as
a cell, it's going to be a lot
plumper of a cell as a result.
So it's going to all build up.
This is known as osmotic pressure.
When it all goes on one entire side.
So this is why you need to make sure
you regulate your salt and sugar
levels in your body because water
can rush from one area to another.
So if you're diabetic or if maybe
you have a very high salt levels in
your body and you need to watch your
food, this is one of the, this is the
reason why, because you can imagine
how this might be applied to cells.
So let's take a look at
applying this to biology then.
When you eat or drink, one thing
that's going to happen is that
your intestines are going to act
like a semi permeable membrane.
So generally what they'll do is, is
they will take out all the water,
all the water that you drink in
will get brought into the body.
So here I'm kind of showing how
water is flowing into the body.
So usually whenever you drink
a lot of water, what's going to
happen is your body tends to have
a higher concentration of solutes.
So it's going to flow out, it's
going to hydrate your cells.
But, what about, why do you
always drink fresh water?
Why can't we drink salt water when there's
so much of it on our planet, right?
97 percent of the water is salt
water, wouldn't it be great if you
could just drink it the way it is?
Well, the reason is why you can't
do it is because of osmosis.
So if you were drinking a very
salty liquid, so think of if your
intestines were full of Salty water.
What's going to happen is when,
because of osmosis, it's going
to flow from an area of low
concentration to high concentration.
So if your body, for example, is
considered to be low concentration,
so let's just say low and what
we have on the inside is high.
So we'll write high here.
It's going to all blow out of
your body and dehydrate you.
So if you ever drink salt water, not
only does it taste gross, but you're
going to start feeling extremely
sick because all of your cells
are now do not have enough water.
And this can be a really big
problem with red blood cells.
Let's take a look at that.
And when it comes to your blood, your
blood cells are something that can
be extremely affected by the amount
of salt and sugar in your body.
So when you're giving IVs to
maybe a patient in the hospital.
They need to make sure that the
levels are appropriate for your
patient so that way their cells
are healthy and hydrated and happy.
So one thing that you're going
to see here is there's three
blood cells in front of you.
We have an isotonic cell.
Now what that refers to is that the level
of essentially the concentration of salt
and sugar are normal inside the cells.
and outside the cell.
So what's going to happen is
pretty much the water is going to
flow in and out nice and happily.
There's going to be no issues at all.
The one on the top in the
middle here is known as a
hypotonic, a hypotonic situation.
So this is when you have essentially a
very, very low sugar or salt in the body.
So let's say if I kind of write,
uh, next to it is if I have low
sugar, in the body, so around it.
So it's in a hypotonic solution.
Well, what's going to happen is inside
of your cell is typically always 0.
9 and 5%.
So let's say if outside
the cell, it was like 0.
4%, and 4.
5 percent sugar, salt
and sugar respectively.
What's going to happen is all of
the water that is now outside is
going to rush inside of the cell.
It's all going to come in.
Now, when that happens, your cell is
going to blow up like a big balloon
and as a result it could pop and end up
actually killing your cell essentially
if you have a too big of an imbalance.
So for people who might be diabetic
and have really low blood sugar, this
is one of the reasons why they're
feeling very lethargic is because their
cells are not functioning properly.
It's not at the right concentration.
So it's very important to regulate levels.
Now the other option is,
let's say if I have my cell.
And let's say on the, uh, inside of the
cell is normal and everything's happy.
So we have 0.
9 percent and 5 percent
for salt and sugar.
Now if the outside is, let's say you
drink a lot of two of really salty foods
and you have a lot of different sugar and
cake and all kinds of really good stuff.
Well, what's going to happen
here is the opposite effect.
Remember from high, or
sorry, from low to high.
So when that happens, we have
really low concentration inside
and everything's going to come out.
Therefore we have a hypertonic cell, which
is when it's going to dehydrate your cell
and cause it to collapse in on itself,
losing its function and its purpose.
So this is some of the factors that can
happen because of colligative properties.
So let's sum it up.
So to sum up everything, the most
important concepts that you need to
know is first is counting how many
particles that you have when you
write your solubility equations.
So you have to write how they dissociate
and fall apart when they're dissolved.
Depending on the number of particles,
the more of them the more of an impact
that your, that your solute will
have on the property of the solution.
Now, next would be molality.
So that'd be the second thing.
So if the particles are the same,
check on the concentration next.
Um, and if they're both the same, then you
look at if it's an ionic molecule versus
covalent, ionic has the stronger impact.
Now, when we're looking at what
properties it has, The solute will
lower the solution's freezing point, so
we can have freezing point depression.
Now, like I said, there's
proportional molality.
Your solute can also raise the solution's
boiling point, so that's why we add
antifreeze, that way it helps prevent
your car from overheating and also can
also prevent it from freezing up as well.
And then the last one is that
solutes can draw water through
membranes, meaning pickling, right?
So pickling or antifreeze or any of these.
So you have freezing point depression,
boiling point elevation, and
osmosis, and that's what you need
to know for colligative properties.
So thank you so much for listening.
As always, I appreciate all of
you for, for whoever watches
and hope you all enjoyed this.
I hope it helped you understand
this concept a little more.
Please, if you have not
already, please like this video.
It helps me grow.
And comment below if you have a question,
I would love to help you as well.
So, and if you haven't yet too,
subscribe to the channel too.
Alright y'all, I hope you have a
wonderful day, and I'll see y'all later.
Bye now!